航空业复苏了……吗？
Air travel is back… with an asterisk.
2019年7月 有79,332,046人通过了美国运输安全局的安检门
In 2019, 79,332,046 people passed through TSA checkpoints in the month of July.
而2021年 这个数字是63,118,017 说明恢复了80%的需求
In 2021, 63,118,017 did—representing an 80% demand recovery.
这个数字打破了大多数专家在2020年的预测 真的很不容易
This blows away most expert forecasts from 2020, and is a remarkable number
尤其考虑到当前国际旅行还一片死寂的形势
considering international travel, and certainly international tourism, is still nearly nonexistent.
在欧洲 航空运输量已经恢复到2019年水平的70%左右
In Europe, air traffic has recovered to around 70% of 2019 levels.
在中国 座席预订量已经超过了2019年的数字——
In China, the number of scheduled seats has already surpassed 2019 numbers—
不但恢复了 还增长了
they're beyond 100% recovery.
因此 美国、欧洲、中国——世界三大航空市场——
So, the US, Europe, and China—the world's three largest aviation markets—
所经历的复苏都超出了之前最乐观的预期
have experienced recoveries beyond the most bullish expectations.
但是……我要说“但是”了
But now, the asterisk.
在2019年第二财季 美国联合航空公司的营收为114.02亿美元
In the second financial quarter of 2019, United Airlines earned $11,402,000,000 in operating revenue.
然而在2021年的同一财季 这个数字只有54.71亿美元——
In the same quarter of 2021, however, just $5,471,000,000—
大约是2019年数字的48%
about 48% of the 2019 number.
同时 美国和达美航空2021年第二财季收入分别是2019年的62.5%和56.8%
Meanwhile, American and Delta's second quarter 2021 revenues
were 62.5% and 56.8%, respectively, compared to 2019.
开头所说的客流恢复并没有使这些数字变得更好
Context does not make these numbers better,
因为在2021年第二季度 通过美国运输安全局检查站的旅客约为2019年的67%
because in the second quarter of 2021, about 67% as many travelers passed through TSA checkpoints as 2019.
简单地说 收入恢复落后于需求恢复
Simply put, revenue recovery is lagging behind demand recovery.
这背后的始作俑者也很容易找到
A culprit is easily identifiable.
在2019年第二季度 美联航每座位每英里的收入为14.32美分——
In the second quarter of 2019, United earned 14.32 cents per seat, per mile flown—
这里其实说的是“revenue per ASM、单位可提供客英里、RASM”
ASM=可供销售的座位数×航段距离
RASM=所有的运营收入/ASM
业内称为“可提供客英里、ASM”（中国叫“可提供客公里、ASK”）
"available seat mile" as its called in the industry.
2021年 美联航的RASM是11.02美分——仅2019年的76.95%
In 2021, they're earning just 11.02 cents per ASM—76.95% of that of 2019.
同时 美航的RASM约为2019年的78.84%
Meanwhile, American's revenue per ASM is at about 78.84% of 2019,
达美航空则为69.45%
while Delta's is 69.45%.
虽然整体收入应完全在整体需求的背景下考虑
While overall revenue should be considered entirely within the context of overall demand,
但RASM并非如此
revenue per ASM should not be.
航空公司自行决定提供多少座位与里程
Airlines decide how many seat miles to make available,
他们决定安排多少航班
they decide how many flights to fly,
因此 航空公司RASM减少20-30%的事实揭开了民航复苏的欢呼声下的秘密
so the fact that airlines are earning some 20-30% less per seat stamps a massive asterisk
on the triumphant calls of travel's return.
坐飞机的人数恢复了 但他们变了
Travelers may be back, but they're not the same.
美国2021年夏季 整个国家似乎都在休假
In the US' summer 2021, the entire country seemingly went on vacation.
夏威夷的希尔顿酒店标价涨到了四季酒店的程度
Hilton's in Hawaii were going for Four Seasons prices,
阿拉斯加的租车业务变成了那些最有远见的旅行者才能负担得起的奢侈品
rental cars in Alaska were a luxury afforded to only the most foresighted travelers,
而拉斯维加斯能打到的出租车就像皇家同花顺一样难遇到
and Ubers in Vegas were as elusive as a royal flush.
2021年夏天 美国的各大旅游景点严重饱和
The US' tourism infrastructure was at absolute peak capacity in summer 2021,
但反观曼哈顿中城、华盛顿特区的K街、芝加哥的环形区——
but then there's this: Midtown Manhattan, DC's K Street, Chicago's Loop—
这些美国的知名商务区仍门可罗雀
America's major business districts still sit abandoned.
尽管日常生活在复苏 但美国国内许多大型白领公司
Despite the resurgence in life in the US, many of the country's largest office-based employers,
像谷歌、微软、苹果、脸书、德勤、思科、麦肯锡这些
including Google, Microsoft, Apple, Facebook, Deloitte, Cisco, and McKinsey,
都还没有真正回到办公室上班
have yet to return to the office in any meaningful way.
这类公司出行肯定是去和别的公司谈生意
When companies of this nature travel, they're doing so to visit other companies,
所以 办公室都还没人来上班 就没有能谈的生意
so, without open offices, there are no companies to visit.
因此 这些在美国出行花费最多的公司
Therefore, the fact these these companies,
which include the top corporate travel spenders in the country,
都还没回办公室上班 解释了为什么商务出行还没有实质上的回归
have yet to return to the office explains why business travel has yet to return meaningfully.
对于美联航、美航、达美、英航、法航、国泰、新加坡、澳洲航空来说——
For United, American, Delta, British Airways, Air France, Cathay Pacific, Singapore Airlines, Qantas—
全都是家喻户晓的老牌国际航空公司——
all the old, storied international airlines that you've heard of—
这是一个非常严重的问题
this represents a disproportionately dramatic problem.
这些“全服务网络”的航空公司基本上是为满足商务出行需求而设计的
These airlines—full-service network carriers, as they're called—are essentially designed
to cater to the needs of business travelers.
以西南航空为例 它是一家以旅游出行为重点的航空公司
Take, for example, the difference between Southwest, a leisure-focused airline,
而美联航是一家以商务出行为重点的航空公司
and United, a business-focused airline.
比如如果有人想从凤凰城前往蒙大拿州的波兹曼参观黄石国家公园
If, for example, someone from Phoenix was traveling to
比如如果有人想从凤凰城前往蒙大拿州的波兹曼参观黄石国家公园Bozeman, Montana to visit Yellowstone National Park,
他可以选择坐西南航空
they could choose to fly on Southwest.
在夏季
During the summer season,
这家航空公司在每个周六和周日上午都有一条直飞航线
this airline operates a nonstop flight on the route each Saturday and Sunday morning.
他还可以坐美联航
The same traveler could also choose to fly on United Airlines,
从丹佛或洛杉矶转机 每天下午6:10、9:40、11:48、1:55或3:41起飞
through either Denver or Los Angeles, leaving at 6:10, 9:40, 11:48, 1:55, or 3:41 pm each day.
然而 旅游出行的人更看重直飞航班的便利性
Leisure travelers, however, disproportionately value the convenience of a nonstop flight
他们不介意在每周有航班的仅有的两天内安排行程
and they wouldn't mind organizing their trip around the two days per week when a flight operates.
但商务出行的人则不同
Business travelers, however, are different.
假设一位来自凤凰城的销售代表需要前往孟菲斯参加一个客户会议
Let's say a sales rep from Phoenix needed to travel to a client meeting in Memphis,
会议时间是星期二下午2点至6点
taking place from 2:00 to 6:00 pm on a Tuesday.
西南航空在这两个城市之间确实有直达航班
Southwest does have a nonstop flight between the cities,
但为了赶上这次会议 该旅客必须乘坐周一的航班
but in order to make that meeting, the traveler would have to take the Monday flight,
中午12:25起飞 下午5:20到达
leaving at 12:25 pm, arriving at 5:20 pm.
然后他们必须在孟菲斯呆上21个小时直到会议开始
They'd then have to sit around in Memphis for 21 hours until the meeting,
然后再等上23个小时的周三下午4点的航班回来
then wait another 23 hours after for the 4:00 pm Wednesday flight back.
然而在美联航 同样的旅客可以在星期二早上6点出发
On United, however, the same traveler could leave at 6:00 am on Tuesday,
经丹佛转机 在下午1点到达 参加下午2点的会议
connect through Denver, arrive at 1:00 pm, make the 2:00 pm meeting,
然后在第二天早上乘坐7点的飞机经休斯顿返回
then take a 7:00 am flight back through Houston the following morning
中午前就能回到办公室 进行这天剩余的工作
and arrive at the office by noon, ready for the rest of the day's work.
面对在孟菲斯多等近一天的情况
Faced with the prospect of waiting around in Memphis for almost a day more,
他们几乎都会选择坐美联航
they'll almost always pick United.
总之 商务出行的人不仅重视出行的日期 而且重视出行的具体时间
In all, business travelers value not only the day of travel, but the time of day of travel.
因此 这些都是各种妥协——你想让航班准确到达你想要的地方
Therefore, it's all a compromise—do you want flights going exactly where you want them to,
还是想让航班在某个特定时间起飞？
or flights leaving exactly when you want them to?
旅游出行看重前者 商务出行看重后者 差别很大
Disproportionately, leisure travelers value the former, business travelers the latter.
这就是为什么几乎所有的美联航、达美和美航的航班都要经停它们的一个枢纽
This is why nearly every United, Delta, and American flight routes through one of their hubs—
通过将旅客整合到更多的定期航班上 前往更少的目的地
by consolidating travelers onto more regular flights to fewer destinations,
它们可以提供更多的航班行程选择
they can offer far more choices of flight itineraries.
对商务出行的优化不止于此
The optimization for business travel extends beyond this
还包括全服务网络航司的高级客舱
to full service network carriers' focus on premium cabins,
常旅客计划、机场服务等等
frequent flyer programs, airport services, and more,
但从根本上说 侧重旅游出行的航司和商务出行的航司之间存在明显区别
but fundamentally, there are stark differences between airlines
made for leisure travelers and those for business travelers,
而世界上许多最大的航空公司都属于后者
and many of the world's largest airlines fall into that second category.
然而从历史上看 这是很值得的
Historically, however, it's been worth it.
商务出行的人全年都在路上 不在乎天气好坏还是学校有没有放假
Business travelers are on the road year round, rather than when the weather is good or school is out,
这意味着他们是航空公司更可靠的客户群体
meaning they represent a more reliable client base for airlines.
此外 他们对价格更没有弹性——
In addition, they're more price inelastic—
也就是说 一个顾问的商务出行需求是硬需求
that's to say, when a consultant needs to travel, they truly need to travel,
票价多高他都得买
and will book a ticket regardless of the price.
相较于旅游出行的人会在机票价格上作出权衡
While leisure travelers will make decisions on price,
企业会不惜一切代价将员工送到需要去的地方 为他们赚钱
businesses will pay whatever it takes to get their staff where they need to go to make them money.
只有大约20%的国内出行是由商务出行进行的
Only about 20% of domestic trips are taken by those on business,
但他们带来的收入远远超过20%
but they account for far more than 20% of revenue.
因为有所谓的“价格歧视”存在
That's because of what's referred to as price discrimination.
它基于一个简单的事实：
It works off of a simple truth:
旅游出行的人绝大多数都是提前几个月制定计划和预订旅行
leisure travelers overwhelmingly make their plans and book trips months in advance,
而商务出行的人则只提前几周或几天
while business travelers book weeks or days in advance.
根据他们自己的财务披露
Based on their own financial disclosures,
我们知道目前美联航的平均飞行长度为1460英里/2350公里
we know that the average United flight length is currently 1,460 miles or 2,350 kilometers,
他们运营此长度的航班的每位乘客平均成本为199.58美元
and that their average cost to operate a flight of that length, per passenger, is $199.58.
我们还知道在两个月前
We also know that, two months before,
美联航正在出售这12个大约1460英里的航班中的8个航班的机票
United is selling tickets for eight of these twelve roughly 1,460 mile flights
价格低于每个乘客的运营成本
for below what it costs to operate on a per-passenger basis.
事实上 这12个航班在起飞前两个月 总体平均票价是低于其运营成本的
In fact, the overall average fare for these twelve flights
sits below their operating cost two months before departure.
虽然出售额外腿部空间的座位
While the sale of ancillaries such as extra legroom seats,
托运行李、Wi-Fi、食品和饮料等附加服务
checked luggage, wifi, food and beverage, and more
可能会推动他们恢复收支平衡
would likely push them above break-even,
但很明显美联航不会以多数平民百姓支付的机票价格来实现大幅盈利
it's clear that United would not turn a significant profit on the prices most of us pay for tickets,
但这一切都是设计好的
but that's by design.
为了装满飞机 他们至少需要在一开始出售廉价机票
To fill planes, they need to sell cheap tickets, at least at first.
然而在飞行前的几周 票价会急剧上升
In the weeks leading up to a flight, however, fares rise dramatically,
所以在起飞前一天 这12个航班平均票价增加了一倍多 达到413.83美元——
so by the day before departure, the average fare for those twelve flights more than doubles to $413.83—
这些通常是企业为他们“十万火急”的商务出行支付的票价
these are the fares businesses are paying for their typically last-minute travel.
现在 在这个平均1460英里的航班上
Now, on that average 1,460 mile flight,
为简单起见 设想由一架179个座位的经济舱737-900飞机来运营
imagine for the sake of simplicity that it was operated by an all-economy, 179 seat 737-900.
根据美联航全公司的载客率 我们知道会有大约150个旅客
We'd know based on United's company-wide load factor that 150 of its seats should be filled.
此时 他们的运营成本将达到29,937美元
In this case, their operating cost would total $29,937.
而他们在该航班上的总收入将是36,245美元
Their total revenue from that flight, however, would be $36,245.
这意味着营收为6,308美元
That means the operating profit margin is $6,308.
再次为简单起见 设想美联航以199.58美元或413.83美元两档价格
Imagining again for the sake of simplicity that United sold this hypothetical,
出售这个假设的 完全平均的航班上的座位
perfectly average flight for either that $199.58 or $413.83 price point,
这将意味着 为了达到平均36,245美元的收入
that would mean, to attain their average $36,245 in revenue,
他们需要出售120张较便宜的机票 主要面向旅游出行的人
they would need to sell 120 of the cheaper tickets, largely to just leisure travelers,
而仅有30张机票以较高价格卖出
and a mere 30 at the higher price point.
这个数字只占售出座位数的20%
That's just 20% of the overall tickets sold on this flight
可你说巧不巧 这个“20%”刚好还等于另一个重要数据：
but 20% happens to represent another important statistic:
美国国内航空出行中商务出行的旅客比例
the average proportion of domestic air travel in the US completed by business travelers.
这种数字上的“巧合”背后并没什么奇怪的
It's not surprising that these numbers work together so perfectly,
因为这正是美联航和其他商务出行为主的航司几十年来一直遵循的数学原理
because this is the exact equation
United and other business-oriented airlines have been using for decades.
在这个假设的航班中 最后的15名乘客 即一半的商务出行者
In the case of this hypothetical flight, its the final 15 passengers, half of the business travelers,
贡献了这条航线的全部利润
that make up the entirety of the airline's profit.
然而现在 在新冠疫情时代 这波客流消失了
Now, however, in the COVID era, they're gone.
西南航空在2021年第二季度每可用座位里程的平均运营成本为10.22美分
Southwest Airlines averaged 10.22 cents
in operating costs per available seat mile in 2021's second quarter,
而美联航的数字是14.49美分——两者的差异非常大
while United averaged 14.49 cents— a dramatic difference,
简单来说 西南航空是一家廉价航空公司
simply explained by the fact that Southwest is a low-cost airline,
意味着其运营成本很低 而美联航不是
meaning its operating costs are low, and United is not.
在现在这种没有无价格弹性的商务出行者的大环境中
In a business environment now devoid of the majority of price inelastic business travelers,
像美联航这样的航空公司已经、且将更难跟上经济复苏的步伐
airlines like United have and will have a lot harder time keeping up with the recovery.
而虽然美联航、达美和美航在第二季度的收入恢复都落后于需求的恢复
While United, Delta, and American's revenue recovery all fell behind demand recovery in the second quarter,
但西南航空却回到了正轨
Southwest's was on-track.
西南航空那边 67%的总体需求恢复带来了67.83%的收入恢复
67% overall demand recovery was, in their case, accompanied by 67.83% revenue recovery.
而现在 随着暑期结束进入9月 这种复苏只会变得更加艰难
And now, as August turns into September, recovery is only going to get tougher.
2021年夏季是许多美国和欧洲旅游景点有史以来最繁忙的时期之一
Summer 2021 was one of the busiest on record for many American and European tourist destinations,
但这段高峰即将结束
but that's coming to an end.
在正常年份 在最繁忙的旅游旺季过后
In a normal year, after a summer lull counterbalanced by the busiest leisure travel season,
商务出行会在九月初开始回升
business travel starts picking up come early September
并在年底前保持在平均水平之上
and stays above average through the end of the year.
这有助于在旅游出行淡季时稳定需求
This helps stabilize demand during a season when few travel for leisure purposes,
但今年 商务出行的这种回暖被阉割了
but this year, that's not going to be there in its full extent.
这种不正常的单向转换已悄然发生
This abnormally one-sided transition is already happening.
美国的旅游需求在7月25日到8月1日这一周下降了2.8%
Travel demand in the US dropped 2.8% between the week of July 25th and August 1st,
然后在8月8日这一周又下降了3%
then another 3% the week of August 8th.
下降幅度不大 但已有初步迹象表明降速比2019年快
It's a small drop, but there are some initial indications that it's happening faster than in 2019,
当时8月的前18天 旅行者比7月的最后18天少4.2%
when the first 18 days of August saw 4.2% fewer travelers than the last 18 days of July.
今年 这两组时间段之间的差异是5.5%
This year, the difference between those two sets of days is 5.5%.
从绝对数值来看似乎不是一个很大的差异
In absolute terms that might not seem like a dramatic difference,
但从相对值来看 这意味着需求下降的速度快了30%
but in relative terms it means the demand drop is happening 30% faster,
而这几周只是旅游出行需求量在夏季结束时的第一个缩减
and these weeks represent only the very first of leisure travel's end of summer retreat.
这种趋势可能会继续下去
This trend will likely continue,
更重要的是 旅游出行需求继续下降 而商务出行需求却未能上升
and, more importantly, accelerate as leisure travel continues to drop, and business travel fails to rise.
在美国 下一个主要旅游旺季要等到11月的感恩节
In the US, the next strong leisure travel period doesn't come until Thanksgiving, in November,
在欧洲是圣诞节
and in Europe, it's Christmas.
当然 德尔塔毒株的肆虐肯定也无济于事
And of course, the Delta variant's spread surely will not help,
因为企业会出于安全考虑而居家办公或者不出差——
as businesses will play it safe with office openings and corporate travel—
现在人们意识到走出疫情的过程本质上并不是线性的
now realizing that the path out of the pandemic is not linear in nature.
对于航空公司来说 目前没什么能做的
For airlines, there's not a whole lot that can be done at this point.
现在这个世界所缺乏的是信心
What the world lacks right now is confidence.
在美国 密歇根大学的消费者情绪指数 跟踪对整体经济状况的信心
In the US, the University of Michigan's consumer sentiment index,
tracking confidence in the overall state in the economy,
在2021年7月和8月之间记录到史上最大的跌幅之一
recorded one of its largest drops in history between July and August 2021.
达到了70.2的水平 比迄今为止大流行病中的任何时候都要低
It reached a level of 70.2, which is lower than any point in the pandemic so far,
也是大衰退以来的最低水平
and its lowest level since the great recession.
这反映了德尔塔毒株及其在后疫苗时代的兴起所带来的不确定性
This is reflective of the amount of uncertainty the Delta variant
and its rise in a post-vaccine era has caused,
尽管在美国 欧洲 英国和其他现在广泛提供疫苗的地方
despite the fact that in the US, Europe, the UK,
and other places where vaccines are now widely available,
住院人数和死亡人数仍然远远低于消费者情绪较高时的水平
hospitalizations and deaths are still far from where they were when consumer sentiment was higher.
然而 如果不能确定大流行病在未来几个月是恶化还是好转
Without the certainty of whether the pandemic will worsen or improve in the coming months, however,
企业就不会做出能够使商务出行需求复苏的重大决定
businesses will not make the big decisions that will bring business travel back.
夏季将可能标志着欧美航空公司在大流行病中的第一个盈利期
Summer will have likely marked
the first profitable period of the pandemic for European and American airlines,
但如果没有强劲的商务出行需求 那么秋季继续恢复其上升趋势似乎希望渺茫
but it seems increasingly unlikely that the recovery will continue its upward trend in fall
without strong business travel.
还有一个问题是 商务出行是否会完全恢复——
There's also the question of whether business travel will ever fully recover—
Zoom：一款远程视频会议软件
大多数专家认为 视频会议会扼杀商务出行的预言被夸大了
most experts believe doomsday predictions of Zoom killing business travel to be overblown,
然而有一种现实的可能性
however, there is a realistic possibility
即2019年可能成为商务出行的历史高水位线
that 2019 could serve as the historical high-water mark for corporate travel
因为大企业的世界正在日益数字化
as the world of big business moves increasingly digital,
对飞往另一个城市吃午餐的环境影响的担忧也在增加
and concerns about the environmental impact of flying to lunch in another city mount.
如果这证实是真的 那么未来几年将发生一些微妙的变化
If this proves true, subtle changes will occur in the coming years
美联航和汉莎可能看起来会更像西南航空和易捷航空
that make United and Lufthansa look more like Southwest and EasyJet.
新冠疫情应该教会航司灵活性与适应性有多么重要
COVID should have taught airlines just how important flexibility and adaptability is.
很难去指责航空公司在危机的深处未能实现盈利
It's hard to fault airlines for failing to turn a profit during the depths of a crisis,
但现在随着大部分发达国家为走出疫情规划出了一条缓慢而坎坷的道路
but now, as much of the developed world plots a slow, bumpy path out of the pandemic,
那就有了盈利的机会
there is opportunity for profitability.
因此 这就是考验真正开始的时候
Therefore, this is when the test truly begins.
这才应该是航空公司所等待的
This is what airlines were waiting for.
所以现在 随着现金储备的减少和投资意愿的消失
So now, with cash reserves wained and investor goodwill gone,
未来几个月对航空公司来说生死攸关
the coming months are truly make or break for airlines.